<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>《智力要素》 on Yingkui</title><link>https://albert.cn/intel/</link><description>Recent content in 《智力要素》 on Yingkui</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Copyright albert.cn All Rights Reserved</copyright><atom:link href="https://albert.cn/intel/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title/><link>https://albert.cn/intel/outline/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://albert.cn/intel/outline/</guid><description>Outline preface
Computation Distinguishability Composition Transformation Max Computation Freedom (Solving Boundary, Fundamental Limitation) Meta-Computation (Facts beyond deterministic) Reverse Computation Abstraction Top-Down Bottom-Up Accumulation of Same Objects Probability: the Indistinguishable Incomplete Information Computation with Abstraction Solving by Searching Guessing by Searching Nearby First Reduction by Computed Result Reduction by Abstract Computed Result Learning without Specific Goals Remembering Object Remember the experienced distinguishable objects Remembering Association Remembering Pattern Generic Solving Algorithm The Robustness v.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://albert.cn/intel/preface/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://albert.cn/intel/preface/</guid><description>Preface The necessity of Turing complete, but not its completeness.
To do all possible computations, we need freedoms that include a few for-all sentences.
The ability to distinguish (has boundary) The ability to recognize The ability to reproduce The ability to use internal representations Access its neighbors freely. Store information freely. The ability to distinguish stuffs is the most fundamental ability for any intelligent agents.
All it cares is that these two objects are different.</description></item><item><title>1.1 Distinguishability</title><link>https://albert.cn/intel/1-1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://albert.cn/intel/1-1/</guid><description>It seems to me that I am rewriting Turing’s paper in a new perspective. The whole first chapter is to reclaim Turing’s idea, but in a way to discuss its necessity but not its completeness. The set of Turing’s abilities is the subset of the total abilities. Distinguishability is</description></item></channel></rss>