<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Yingkui Lin</title><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/</link><description>Recent content on Yingkui Lin</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Copyright Yingkui.com All Rights Reserved</copyright><atom:link href="https://yingkui.com/mv/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/_preface/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/_preface/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;70-80 articles，1400 words each article，100K words total.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you think, you should always think in terms of words and dollars, which are quantifiable forms of vocabulary and money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Repetition is a strategy of this book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;这世上还没有什么书，是一本一生必读之书，这世上有很多学问，却没有一本书囊括生命中大多关键本质，&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;而这本书就一部尝试这种类别的书，一部一生只看一本书，就应该看类似这样书，或许不是这本书，至少从类别上，就是一本这样的书。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;作为一个有着不切实际目标的作品，它主要传递的就是两个观点：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;如何把人生的所有行为和目标，都转化成钱的角度，有形的又或者是无形的收益语言，如何这样一个统一的视角能更让我们清晰的知道人生的目标&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;如何把求知，把科学进展，把对世界的理解，都转化为词汇的角度，具体的词汇（比如，大象）又或者是抽象的词汇（比如，勇敢），如何这样一个把知识都融合到一起的做法能极大的提高我们思考的效率，能够更加快速的直击问题的本质&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/academia/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/academia/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="the-pleasure-of-finding-things-out"&gt;The Pleasure of Finding Things Out&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a unique thrill in discovery that transcends the mere acquisition of knowledge. When we stumble upon something unexpected, when patterns suddenly emerge from chaos, or when we grasp a concept that had long eluded us, we experience a rush of pleasure that is both intellectual and visceral. This joy of discovery is perhaps most eloquently captured in the excited &amp;ldquo;Eureka!&amp;rdquo; of Archimedes, but it lives on in every moment of revelation, from a child&amp;rsquo;s first understanding of why the sky is blue to a physicist&amp;rsquo;s recognition of a new fundamental particle.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/advance/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/advance/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="rhythmic-innovation-the-resistance-to-progress-and-the-power-of-conservatism"&gt;Rhythmic Innovation: The Resistance to Progress and the Power of Conservatism&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Introduction – Innovation Needs Rhythm
Innovation is often portrayed as a relentless march forward—new technologies, radical ideas, and disruptive models. Yet history shows that innovation rarely succeeds in a vacuum. It thrives when it meets the friction of social norms, existing institutions, and cautious adoption. This “rhythm” of innovation—push, test, slow down, adjust, then advance again—keeps societies from collapsing under the weight of untested changes.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/against/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/against/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Why Formal Learning and Huge Money-Making Feel Painful — and Why People Must Be Pushed&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Nature of Deep Knowledge and Large-Scale Enterprise&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Formal learning and large-scale business creation share a common trait: they require sustained, structured effort far beyond the threshold of casual interest. Deep knowledge in mathematics, science, or history takes thousands of hours of deliberate study. Similarly, building a major enterprise involves navigating regulation, financing, hiring, product-market fit, and competitive strategy over years. Both processes demand delayed gratification, intense focus, and resilience against failure.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/ambiguity/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/ambiguity/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="blur-and-equivalence-the-power-of-the-hard-to-distinguish"&gt;Blur and Equivalence: The Power of the Hard-to-Distinguish&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In every sphere of life, from physics to politics to everyday marketing, one tactic repeatedly emerges: making two things appear equivalent or indistinguishable so that observers lose their critical edge. This technique, which could be called blur and equivalence, harnesses ambiguity to achieve power. When categories are blurred and boundaries softened, people struggle to distinguish what is true, fair, or valuable. That confusion can be weaponized.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/anxiety/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/anxiety/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="因为词汇带来的情绪"&gt;因为词汇带来的情绪&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id="fomo"&gt;FOMO&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id="炫耀"&gt;炫耀&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;我小时候会因为自己懂一些椭圆知识而很有自豪感&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lexical Anxiety and Showing Off: Overvaluing Rare Words&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FOMO for the Unknown&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In everyday life, people constantly worry about missing out on the latest news, memes, or trending topics. This is a kind of lexical FOMO: the fear that if you don’t know the name of the new scandal, the viral video, or the trending catchphrase, you’ll seem uninformed or “out of the loop.” It’s less about genuine curiosity and more about social survival — knowing what others know so you won’t feel excluded.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/authoritarian/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/authoritarian/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="集体粗鄙"&gt;集体粗鄙&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Collectively Vulgar&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在人类社会中，个体的精神缺陷往往是局部的，但当权力机制将这些缺陷放大到集体层面时，整个社会就会表现得像一个庞大而迟钝的低智个体。专制体制之下，国家、社会、群体的行为模式，常常与一个人格障碍者相似：自恋、粗俗、短视、无趣。这种“集体粗鄙”既是一种病理，也是专制统治不可避免的副产物。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;一、自恋：膨胀的自我幻象
专制社会的第一个特征是自恋。它强调自身的伟大与独特，拒绝承认缺陷，害怕比较与竞争。正如自恋个体需要不断的外部赞美来维持脆弱的自我，专制社会依赖宣传机器和控制舆论来构筑幻象。它的自信并非基于真实的成就，而是通过否认、遮蔽和粉饰维持的脆弱表象。这种集体自恋让社会失去了自我反思的能力，只能陷入不断自我陶醉的闭环。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;二、品味低下：庸俗的文化审美
当社会的最高标准不是自由、真理与创造，而是“听话”“服从”“讨好”，文化必然走向粗鄙化。专制体制下的文艺往往流于媚俗、献媚、迎合权力，失去了独立精神与批判锋芒。像低智个体沉迷于浮夸的装饰与炫耀，专制社会的文化品味也被庸俗的符号和廉价的感官刺激所占据。真正深刻的思想与艺术被边缘化，整个社会审美退化为浅薄、空洞的娱乐化。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;三、社会达尔文主义：弱肉强食的伪理性
在专制语境下，“适者生存”被误读为赤裸的强者逻辑。社会失去了对弱者的怜悯与保护，取而代之的是对权力与财富的盲目崇拜。人与人之间的关系，不再是基于平等与尊严的契约，而是赤裸裸的等级支配。这种逻辑像低智个体的思维方式：非黑即白，唯强是尊。它掩盖了合作、共情和制度正义的重要性，把社会推向犬儒与冷酷。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;四、拜金：认钱、认劝的庸俗算计
专制社会往往将金钱与权力视为唯一的衡量标准。社会成员逐渐丧失了独立判断力，把“谁更有钱、谁更能说服权力”当作唯一真理。这种价值观是一种“低维度”的生存策略，类似低智个体的短视本能：只懂得追逐眼前利益，而无法理解长期价值与公共善。结果是社会整体陷入庸俗的功利主义，精神与道德被彻底边缘化。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;五、集体粗鄙的逻辑
为什么专制社会会退化为一个“粗俗低智的个体”？原因在于权力结构本身消解了复杂性与多样性。自由社会像一个多元的网络，思想可以交锋、价值能够互补，因此智慧得以涌现。而专制则像一个单向度的脑回路，所有输入与输出必须经过权力核心的过滤，复杂被简化，深度被压扁。最终，社会集体的智力水平不再是众人智慧的总和，而是退化为最低层次的“本能反应”。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;结语
一个自恋、庸俗、短视、拜金的个体，也许只会在私人生活中制造混乱。但当整个社会沦为这样的集体人格时，灾难就是必然。所谓“集体粗鄙”，正是专制社会最深层的写照。它提醒我们：真正的文明，不仅在于科技与财富的积累，更在于能否建立起一个使集体智慧超越个体本能的制度结构。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;自恋：关闭外部反馈，降低 surprise 的“廉价办法”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在 FEP 中，系统要不断修正模型来匹配现实。但专制社会往往拒绝面对真实世界的复杂反馈，因为那会增加认知 dissonance（预测误差）。于是它选择最“省力”的办法：通过宣传、信息控制来强行消除预测误差。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;例如，社会宣称“我们是最优越的文明”，即使现实与之矛盾，也通过屏蔽证据来维持“低 surprise”。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;这种自恋不是智慧的体现，而是懒惰的模型修正：不通过学习来改进模型，而是通过否认现实来减少预测误差。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;换句话说，这是 一种病态的最小化自由能：追求表面的低惊讶，而牺牲长期的学习与适应。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;品味低下：选择低复杂度的 generative model&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在 FEP 中，学习需要构建足够复杂的生成模型去解释数据。但复杂的模型需要能量、需要算力。专制社会倾向于选取最简单、最粗鄙的解释框架，因为这能降低计算成本。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;高雅的思想、艺术、批判会带来高熵和不可预测性。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;粗鄙的口号、低俗的娱乐、审美媚俗，反而是低复杂度的“模型”，可以快速被大多数人接受，减少认知负担。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;因此，文化粗俗化是一种“低能量解法”：以牺牲深度与多样性，来维持最低限度的“预测成功率”。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;社会达尔文主义：把不确定性转嫁给个体&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="专制的逻辑"&gt;专制的逻辑&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FEP 强调系统要减少 surprise。但专制政体往往把这种负担转嫁给个体：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;体制本身不优化结构，而是通过社会达尔文主义告诉个人“成败全在你自己”。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;这样，系统不用承担复杂的环境预测，只要维持等级秩序，个体之间的竞争与淘汰自然会“减少不确定性”。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;这类似于一个粗暴的神经网络：它不改进整体结构，而是通过丢弃大量“错误样本”来减少误差。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;拜金主义（认钱、认劝）：使用单一 reward signal&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在一个健全的社会，预测误差的校正需要多维度的奖励信号（公平、真理、美感、合作）。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;但专制社会会把 reward 简化为单一维度：金钱或权力。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;因为多维价值会带来高复杂度的建模成本。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;用钱和权力作为唯一的“precision weighting”（权重），整个社会的学习过程就变成了“谁有资源，谁说得算”。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;这是一种 低维度的世界建模：虽然简单，但导致社会智力退化，只剩下最庸俗的追逐。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;从 Markov Blanket 的视角看，专制的存在方式就是用最低智力的办法守住边界&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;整个系统在运作时刻意压低复杂度，把认知、文化、制度的精细度压缩到最低层次。这样反而有利于权力集中和压迫&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;高智社会需要复杂的 generative model 来解释世界：科学、批判、新闻、司法等多维机制。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;这些高复杂度输入会带来大量 prediction error，需要不断修正内部模型。这样，权力中心也会被迫接受挑战。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;专制选择“低智模型”：只允许单一维度解释世界。这样 Markov Blanket 的边界变得简单，输入输出关系容易控制。&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/bayes/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/bayes/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="bayes"&gt;Bayes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id="pbmid-a"&gt;$P(B\mid A)$&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The equation $E=mc^2$ may be the most celebrated in science, but its practical impact on our everyday lives is limited it dazzles more than it delivers. Even Feynman’s championing of atomic theory, though fundamentally important, doesn’t always translate into direct, universal benefits. In contrast, the principle of Bayesian inference expressed as&lt;/p&gt;
$$
P(B\mid A)
$$&lt;p&gt;the probability of $B$ given that $A$ has occurred provides a versatile, widely applicable tool for updating beliefs and guiding decisions in countless real‑world situations.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/bd/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/bd/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="广度还是深度"&gt;广度还是深度&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id="偏差与方差"&gt;偏差与方差&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3 id="决策权绩优主义与反智主义"&gt;决策权：绩优主义与反智主义&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3 id="治理方式紧急状态和无政府主义"&gt;治理方式：紧急状态和无政府主义&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3 id="科研经费基础科学与集邮主义"&gt;科研经费：基础科学与集邮主义&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3 id="英雄崇拜还是去中心化"&gt;英雄崇拜还是去中心化&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3 id="节目效果还是苦行僧"&gt;节目效果还是苦行僧&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3 id="不确定原理"&gt;不确定原理&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3 id="最小能量原理"&gt;最小能量原理&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Depth or Breadth: The Ubiquitous Trade-Off&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Across science, engineering, and everyday life, we constantly face a fundamental tension: depth versus breadth. This is not a minor inconvenience but a structural feature of complex systems. The same way a computer scientist must choose between depth-first search (DFS) and breadth-first search (BFS), human beings must decide between accuracy and efficiency, between focus and flexibility, between digging deeper and reaching wider.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/better/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/better/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="2-trivial-bragging"&gt;2. Trivial Bragging&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trivial bragging manifests in everyday social interactions in ways that can range from playful commentary to deliberate attempts to impress. This behavior often focuses on seemingly minor achievements or displays of obscure knowledge that carry little practical relevance. While sharing fun facts or niche insights can foster curiosity and connection, trivial bragging shifts into pretension when it is used as a way to belittle others or highlight their lack of knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/breath/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/breath/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The Price of Breath&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every breath comes with a price. It&amp;rsquo;s a burden as old as life itself, unchanging in its necessity yet ever-shifting in its form. From the first humans who walked the Earth to those who now walk among skyscrapers, we share this fundamental truth: existence demands payment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our ancestors understood this price intimately. They paid it in the countless hours spent hunting, in the backbreaking work of tilling soil, in the careful maintenance of their tools and shelters. A farmer&amp;rsquo;s life meant rising before dawn, tending to animals, watching the skies for weather that could destroy a year&amp;rsquo;s work. A craftsman&amp;rsquo;s existence meant years of learning their trade, providing value to their community through their work. They paid in resources stored for winter, in implements that needed repair, in clothes that needed mending, in relationships that needed nurturing.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/conditions/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/conditions/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="modern-civilization-has-outstripped-the-conditions-our-minds-evolved-for"&gt;Modern Civilization Has Outstripped the Conditions Our Minds Evolved For&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Introduction: An Evolutionary Mismatch&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Human brains evolved in a radically different environment from today’s. For hundreds of thousands of years, our ancestors lived in small, nomadic groups, facing immediate threats, limited resources, and social structures based on face-to-face interaction. Yet in the last few centuries—barely a blink on an evolutionary timescale—industrialization, urbanization, and digital technology have transformed our environment. This mismatch between our evolved capacities and modern conditions is the central reason why the brain we have is poorly suited to modern life.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/confirm/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/confirm/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="确认偏差"&gt;确认偏差&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;习惯性的站在自己观点的对立面&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id="什么是确认偏差"&gt;什么是确认偏差？&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;人们更倾向于寻找、记住、解释那些支持自己已有信念或观点的信息，而忽略或轻视与自己信念相矛盾的信息。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;例如，如果你相信星座性格分析，说“射手座外向爱自由”，你就会特别注意到射手座朋友外向的一面，而忽略他们安静、不爱社交的时刻。
结果是，你感觉“星座真的很准”，但其实只是确认偏差在起作用。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;如果某人强烈爱国，他会更愿意相信强调国家成就、民族团结的新闻或评论，并觉得这些信息可信。
但当他看到批评国家的问题（腐败、环境污染、人权问题等）的报道时，就会觉得“不真实”“这是外国势力抹黑”，甚至直接不去看。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;如果某人强烈反感专制，他会更愿意相信揭露专制体制弊端的新闻，并觉得这些信息合乎事实。
当他看到一些强调“稳定”“秩序”或专制制度带来经济发展好处的文章时，就会觉得“这是洗地”“有偏见”，甚至拒绝阅读。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="为什么会有确认偏差"&gt;为什么会有确认偏差？&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;智能有机体更新内部世界模型（belief revision）是一件代价极高的事情，需要耗费大量认知资源。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;因此，系统更倾向于保持原有模型稳定，只要还能合理解释当下数据。确认偏差可以起到“延缓大规模修正”的作用。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;当一个人同时持有 两个相互矛盾的信念、态度或行为 时，会产生心理上的紧张和不适，这种状态就叫 认知失调。在情绪上，符合预期的信息会带来“模型正确”的确认感，降低惊讶，生理上产生奖励体验，相反的信息会引起不安、不适，意味着要面对新的世界模型，因此人会主动回避。如果承认自己错了，会产生认知失调（心理痛苦）。为了减少痛苦，人们往往更愿意找支持证据来“证明自己没错”，&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;确认偏差不仅是认知上的自由能最小化，也是 情感上减少不适 的一种表现。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;虚荣心的自我保护，虚荣心的一个核心功能是维持“我是正确的”“我是有价值的”这种自我形象。当出现相反证据时，虚荣心会感到威胁，于是大脑会通过确认偏差来过滤掉“打脸”的信息。在某些社会环境中，“认错”意味着丢面子或社会地位下降。于是个体更倾向坚持原有观点，哪怕事实在眼前。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="确认偏差的害处"&gt;确认偏差的害处&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;个人层面，妨碍学习和成长，总是只接受符合自己观点的信息，导致视野狭窄。知识结构难以更新，思维停留在固有模式里。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;降低决策质量，在做重要选择（买房、择业、投资等）时，忽略不利证据，容易高估利好，低估风险，最后可能做出错误甚至灾难性的决定。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;自我欺骗与情绪困境，只接受让自己舒服的信息，从而短期减少焦虑，但长期可能导致与现实脱节。当现实“打脸”时，心理冲击会更大。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;与他人沟通障碍，在争论时，不是听对方的理由，而是不断寻找反驳的证据。结果是对话失效，双方更固执。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;加剧偏见和刻板印象，比如“某一类人都怎样”，只记得符合偏见的个案，忽视反例，导致误解、歧视，滋生没有必要的矛盾。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;信息茧房，人们只在同类群体里交流，互相强化同样的观点。结果是立场越来越极端，对立越来越尖锐。公民若只接收“有利于自己立场”的新闻，会加深社会撕裂，难以达成共识。极端情况下，可能导致群体对抗甚至冲突。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="认知模型复杂度不足"&gt;认知模型复杂度不足&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;认知模型简单的人，他们的大脑倾向于用单一框架解释世界，只能容纳一种答案。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;当遇到矛盾证据时，就会产生不适，因为这意味着模型需要拆解和重建，而这对他们来说很困难或几乎不可能。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;所以，他们会下意识拒绝“打脸证据”，只保留符合预期的信息，也就确认偏差更强。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;认知模型简单的人更容易陷入“非黑即白”的思维，无法处理失调，从而依赖确认偏差来保护自己&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;认知模型复杂的人，他们能够在头脑中并行存储多个可能的解释，甚至允许矛盾观点共存。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;这种情况下，遇到冲突信息不会立刻造成巨大心理负担，因此确认偏差的倾向会相对弱一些。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;认知模型复杂的人能容忍失调，把冲突当作信息源，而不是威胁。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;一个简单模型的人，像一个“怕冷的人”，总要立刻关掉冷风（短期舒适），哪怕因此永远待在狭小的屋子里。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;一个复杂模型的人，像一个“能忍短期寒冷的人”，敢于走出去收集木柴和食物。虽然一时不舒服（短期自由能高），但最终获得更大安全感（长期自由能低）。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="提高认知复杂度"&gt;提高认知复杂度&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;大脑的默认模式是倾向于“快思维”，也就是追求确定性，简化模型，快速降低自由能。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;一个人越常接触复杂信息、矛盾观点，大脑就越会重塑连接，也就更容易形成分层模型。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;需要容忍不确定、接受矛盾、不断修正，这和大脑的“节能本能”是相反的，也就是需要刻意的训练，来取代本能的低效和偏差。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;接触多元信息，主动去看不同立场的观点（比如一条新闻的正反评论），而不是只泡在信息茧房&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;练习批判性思维，对同一问题，尝试列出两种或更多解释，并检验各自的证据，这训练大脑能“并行存储多个假设”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;培养不确定性耐受力，刻意去面对模棱两可的问题，不急着下结论，而不是逃避思考，认为思考是无意义和徒劳的&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="统计学理解"&gt;统计学理解&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在确认偏差下，人类的“更新公式”并不是完整的，而是带有偏权重：&lt;/p&gt;
$$
P^*(H \mid D) \propto 
\begin{cases} 
w_1 \cdot P(D \mid H) P(H), &amp; D \ \text{支持原有信念} \newline
w_2 \cdot P(D \mid H) P(H), &amp; D \ \text{反对原有信念} 
\end{cases}
$$&lt;p&gt;其中：&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/convert/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/convert/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="钱词转化"&gt;钱词转化&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lexeme = 投资标的&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;词位 (lexeme) 就像一只股票或资产：它代表着一种“解释力 + 压缩力”。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;当大脑获得一个 lexeme，就像投资者买入了一种“快速压缩世界的工具”。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;比如：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;买了 “爱” 这个 lexeme → 很多复杂的体验瞬间能打包。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;买了 “外部眼光” 这个 lexeme → 很多行为都能用“别人怎么看”解释&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;投资收益 = 认知回报&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;高价值 lexeme：能长期降低自由能，帮助你压缩复杂经验，解释范围广且稳定。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;类似“价值股”，虽然短期没有强烈刺激，但长期复利。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;例子：长期价值、真实兴趣、成长、因果。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;低价值 lexeme：只能带来短期快感，长期没有复利效应，甚至让模型越来越脆弱。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;类似“骗子股”或“垃圾股”。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;例子：外部眼光、面子至上、他人评价。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;投资成本 = 认知消耗&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;每买一个 lexeme，实际上要付出：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;注意力（要反复调用）&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;认知资源（要用它来解释输入）&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;情绪能量（要承担波动带来的影响）&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;如果一个 lexeme 带来的是 持续消耗 + 偶尔的小回报，那就是亏本投资。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;投资决策：需求与陷阱&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;你说的“需求就是想得到一个 lexeme，但这个 lexeme 不值得你得到”，可以类比为：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;需求：就像投资者渴望一个“解释世界的工具”，因为没有 lexeme 会很焦虑。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;陷阱：市场上有很多“低质 lexeme”，它们看似能立刻满足需求，但长期价值为负。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;就像投资人渴望一支能涨的股票，于是被骗子公司画的大饼吸引。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;外部眼光就是这样的 lexeme → 它满足了“我是谁”的焦虑，却带来长期负债。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;从投资角度看，lexeme 是一种“认知资产”。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;好的 lexeme = 长期价值股 → 持有越久越划算。&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/core/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/core/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="钱与词"&gt;钱与词&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;学词，挖词，用词，幻觉&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="lexeme-的定义"&gt;Lexeme 的定义&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lexeme 是指：人类在学习与思考过程中形成的、具有压缩性和预测力的认知单位。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;它通过建立一个 Markov blanket（边界），在内部形成稳定的结构，用于减少外部世界带来的 surprise（预测误差）。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;换句话说，lexeme 就是一个 能显著降低不确定性、提高预测效率的“知识粒子”。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;它既可以是一个单词（如“能量”）、一个抽象概念（如“博弈”）、一条定理（如“熵增定律”），甚至可以是一个模式（如“供需曲线”）。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;压缩性 (Compression)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;能把大量复杂的信息压缩成一个简洁的符号或概念。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;例如“重力”一词就压缩了苹果落地、潮汐变化、行星轨道等现象。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;预测力 (Predictive Power)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;一个 lexeme 的价值在于它能帮助我们更准确地预测未来，降低 surprise。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;比如“供需关系”能让我们预测价格变动。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Markov Blanket 性质 (Boundary Property)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;每个 lexeme 都像一个局部模型，有自己的输入（外部刺激）、内部状态（结构）、输出（预测/行动）。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;通过与环境交互，它形成一个“边界”，在边界内自洽运作。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;可组合性 (Composability)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;lexeme 可以彼此组合，形成更复杂的表达或理论。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;例如“能量 + 守恒”组合成“能量守恒定律”。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;分层性 (Hierarchical Nature)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;lexeme 之间有层级：底层 lexeme（具体词汇/经验） → 高层 lexeme（抽象理论/范式）。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;高层 lexeme 学习慢但压缩更强。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;学习成本 (Acquisition Cost)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;每个 lexeme 都有学习门槛，取决于先验知识、复杂度和抽象程度。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;简单 lexeme 学得快（“苹果”），复杂 lexeme 需要共识与长期学习（“相对论”）。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;情感与动机附着 (Affective Stickiness)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;lexeme 往往带有情感色彩或价值意义，使其在记忆与传播中更稳定。&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/daddy/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/daddy/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="the-psychology-of-worship-and-the-dark-triad"&gt;The Psychology of Worship and the Dark Triad&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why We Worship&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Humans have a long history of elevating certain individuals to near-mythical status. This tendency to worship arises from deep evolutionary and psychological roots. In uncertain or complex environments, our brains crave simplicity and authority. By deifying a figure—be it a political leader, a celebrity, a business magnate, or even a “father figure”—we reduce ambiguity and transfer responsibility. This gives us a sense of order and belonging. It also satisfies emotional needs for security, guidance, and validation, especially in times of crisis. When people feel powerless or lack a stable personal authority figure, their longing for such a figure intensifies. This dynamic is why paternal archetypes—leaders who present themselves as “protectors” or “fathers of the nation”—can evoke strong loyalty.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/dark/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/dark/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="grand-ambition-shallow-talent-confronting-the-absurdity-and-darkness-of-the-world"&gt;Grand Ambition, Shallow Talent: Confronting the Absurdity and Darkness of the World&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The phrase, &amp;ldquo;great aspiration, shallow talent,&amp;rdquo; describes a profound and painful misalignment: the vast, towering ambition of an individual coupled with a crippling lack of corresponding ability or sustained effort. This condition is the engine of a specific, modern tragedy. It describes not merely failure, but the soul-deep bitterness of those who believe they are owed a great destiny by the universe, only to find the universe stubbornly refuses to pay its debt. When such a gap becomes irreconcilable, the resulting psychological landscape is often one of perceived absurdity and darkness.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/death/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/death/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In the tapestry of human experience, we find ourselves suspended between two vast darknesses – the void that preceded our birth and the eternal silence that awaits us in death. Yet between these twin abysses blazes a brief but brilliant flash of consciousness, a flame of being that burns with incredible intensity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life unfolds before us in an endless cascade of sensations and moments. There&amp;rsquo;s the first sip of coffee on a crisp morning, steam rising like prayers to the dawn. There&amp;rsquo;s the laughter of children echoing across a playground, each peal a celebration of pure, unfiltered joy. We experience the electric touch of a loved one&amp;rsquo;s hand, the satisfaction of creating something beautiful, the peace of watching snow fall in perfect silence. Even in our mundane routines, we find small miracles – the way sunlight dapples through leaves, the purr of a cat curled in our lap, the taste of fresh bread still warm from the oven.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/democracy/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/democracy/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="consensus"&gt;Consensus&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consensus, a term often used to describe a general agreement among a group, is a concept that permeates various aspects of human society. It represents a collective view on a particular matter, whether it be a scientific theory, a political decision, or an economic policy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the realm of science, consensus refers to the shared understanding among experts in a specific field. It is reached through rigorous peer review, experimentation, and the accumulation of evidence. Scientific consensus is not a static concept but rather an evolving one, shaped by new discoveries and advancements. It provides a solid foundation for further research and innovation, guiding scientists towards promising avenues of inquiry.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/dirty/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/dirty/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="kitsch-and-cheating-why-wealth-and-powers-success-is-not-always-glamorous"&gt;Kitsch and Cheating: Why Wealth and Power’s Success Is Not Always Glamorous&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Hidden Shadows of Wealth and Power
Success, wealth, and power are often wrapped in a glamorous aura, celebrated as the ultimate proof of competence and value. Yet behind this veneer lies a darker story. Throughout history, many fortunes were not built solely on innovation, effort, or virtue but on deception, exploitation, or outright violence. From ancient kings and emperors to modern tycoons, the narratives of glory often conceal the human cost beneath.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/edu/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/edu/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="intellectual-stamina"&gt;Intellectual Stamina&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intellectual stamina refers to the capacity to maintain focused mental effort over extended periods, particularly when engaging with complex or challenging cognitive tasks. It&amp;rsquo;s analogous to physical endurance but applies to mental activities, enabling individuals to persist in deep thinking, problem-solving, and learning without succumbing to mental fatigue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Real-Life Examples
In academia, a researcher analyzing complex data sets for hours while maintaining accuracy demonstrates intellectual stamina. Similarly, a chess grandmaster competing in a tournament that spans several hours must sustain intense concentration and strategic thinking throughout multiple matches. Software developers often need to maintain mental focus while debugging intricate code or architecting complex systems, sometimes for extended coding sessions.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/ego/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/ego/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="虚荣心降低对他人评价的过拟合"&gt;虚荣心：降低对他人评价的过拟合&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id="高层"&gt;高层&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在 FEP 框架下，个体大脑维护一个分层的 生成模型：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;低层：感官输入、即时威胁（生理上的危险、疼痛、死亡风险）。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;中层：社会评价、自我价值感、他人眼光。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;高层：核心自我模型、意义、身份认同（“我是一个体面的人”“我有尊严”）。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;虚荣心（对外部评价的高度敏感）其实是高层模型稳定性的关键部分：它将“外界他人看法”内化为“自我存在的正确性”。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;生物体的目标是最小化自由能（即惊讶/预测误差）。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;肉体死亡：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在高层模型里，死亡是可能的“终点事件”，有某种程度的可预测性（比如战争、疾病、风险本身已被纳入世界模型）。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;所以“被杀”虽然是负面，但并不必然撕裂身份模型的核心结构。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;羞辱/侮辱：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;羞辱直接冲击高层身份模型：“我是谁”的预测和现实彻底不符。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;当别人公开否认、贬低、嘲笑时，个体的社会存在感、价值感被颠覆，导致极大自由能增加，因为高层模型无法再解释低层证据。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;换句话说，辱会动摇整套生成模型的顶层假设，比死亡更难以“吸收”。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;所以“可杀不可辱”是说：与其承受整个身份模型崩塌的预测误差，还不如终止生命模型本身。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在自由能原则的层级推理框架下，“可杀不可辱”揭示了 虚荣心作为高层自我模型核心 的地位。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;它不仅仅是“情绪”或“面子”，而是大脑维持预测闭合、压缩世界模型的最高级支柱。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="历史上的极端"&gt;历史上的极端&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;中国传统：“名节”高于生命。文天祥《正气歌》“人生自古谁无死，留取丹心照汗青”。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;日本武士道：受辱即切腹。肉体毁灭可以被接受，但身份污损不可。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;西方骑士 / 贵族：决斗文化。如果名誉受损，必须用生死对抗来修复模型。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="原因"&gt;原因&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;群体生存依赖合作与承认。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;社会评价 ≈ 生存先验概率。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;因此虚荣心不仅是“爱面子”，而是演化出的自我模型的基石：丢了面子 ≈ 丢了社会生存条件。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;进化论角度：群居生物的适应机制&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;个体生存靠群体
人类并非独居动物，生存与繁衍高度依赖群体协作。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;社会评价决定生存概率
在远古部落，如果你被群体排斥（被羞辱、失去地位），那几乎等于死亡（没食物、没人保护）。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;虚荣心 = 适应性信号
所以对他人眼光高度敏感，是一种本能的“早期预警系统”。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;面子 ≈ 生存先验概率&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;失去尊重 ≈ 生存风险上升&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;因此，ego 是演化出来的“社会生存本能”。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;它是多层叠加的结果：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;生物层 → 群居演化的生存策略&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;认知层 → 高层模型需要社会角色闭合&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;心理层 → 成长过程中不断内化的“他人眼光”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="危害"&gt;危害&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;过度精确化（precision overweighting）
在 FEP 里，每个预测都带有精度（置信度）。&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/emo/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/emo/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;懒散、恐慌、贪婪&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-cost-of-comfort-when-emotional-agents-lead-to-substantial-loss"&gt;The Cost of Comfort: When Emotional Agents Lead to Substantial Loss&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the complex landscape of modern commerce and personal affairs, from financial investments to real estate transactions, individuals frequently rely on agents or third-party service providers. While many operate with integrity, a specific type of deceptive intermediary thrives by prioritizing the client’s emotional value—a fleeting sense of certainty, superiority, or ease—over their substantive, long-term success. These &amp;ldquo;harmful agents&amp;rdquo; master the art of emotional manipulation, preying on our most fundamental human feelings—pride, sloth, greed, fear, and anxiety—to convince us to accept a suboptimal outcome, thus causing us to “sacrifice the greater for the lesser.”&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/emotions/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/emotions/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="emotions"&gt;Emotions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;emotional regulation. It’s not about suppressing feelings or becoming a robot&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emotional regulation is the ability to notice, understand, and manage your emotional responses so they don’t hijack your behavior&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of being yanked around by every spike of fear, anger, or shame, you can feel those emotions and still choose your response.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you feel attacked, your amygdala floods your system with stress hormones. If you can regulate that surge, you create the mental space to listen, consider new evidence, and update your views rather than reflexively refute them.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/empathy/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/empathy/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="self-centeredness-how-a-lack-of-empathy-resembles-dining-and-dashing"&gt;Self-Centeredness: How a Lack of Empathy Resembles Dining and Dashing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In everyday life, we recognize the unfairness of a “dine-and-dash” — when someone eats at a restaurant but leaves without paying. Yet when it comes to relationships, work, or community, many people behave in an almost identical way, but emotionally or socially rather than financially. They take time, energy, or kindness from others without any intention of giving back. This dynamic captures the essence of the title: a lack of empathy is functionally equivalent to “eating a meal without paying the bill.”&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/end/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/end/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="ai-is-the-end-of-life"&gt;AI is the end of life&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the End of the Ladder: What Now?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Humanity has spent centuries climbing a “heavenly ladder” of progress — from agriculture to industry, from electricity to the digital age. Each rung has carried us higher, promising freedom, abundance, and knowledge. Yet at the top of this ladder, we are beginning to sense limits. Many of us feel exhausted, alienated, or locked into repetitive work despite our unprecedented technological power. The question naturally arises: What should we do at the end of this ladder?&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/escape/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/escape/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="escaping-failure-vanity-over-ambition"&gt;Escaping Failure: Vanity Over Ambition&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modern life presents countless opportunities to strive, create, and improve. Yet many people quietly avoid true ambition and instead nurture vanity—maintaining an image of success rather than pursuing genuine progress. This phenomenon, which we can call “escaping failure,” is not simply laziness; it is a psychological strategy that prioritizes appearance over reality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Fear of Failure and the Safe Path&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ambition by definition exposes us to risk. Applying for a demanding job, learning a difficult skill, or starting a new venture all invite possible failure and public embarrassment. Vanity offers a tempting alternative: one can craft a curated persona, highlight small victories, or adopt the identity of a “promising” individual without testing oneself in a meaningful arena. By doing this, people shield their egos from rejection while still harvesting social approval.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/established/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/established/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="within-the-establishment"&gt;Within the Establishment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the complex architecture of modern society, the allure of belonging to prestigious institutions has become a defining feature of success. Yet, beneath the veneer of prestige and legitimacy lies a system that is not only fiercely competitive but often riddled with paradoxes. The pursuit of elite positions within bureaucracies, corporations, and other powerful establishments reveals a troubling dynamic: a system where the rewards far outweigh the contributions, where pride in status often supersedes the drive to produce meaningful value.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/existance/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/existance/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The reasons of being and the reasons of to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-meaning-of-life"&gt;The Meaning of Life&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contemplating the meaning of life, we often find ourselves searching for something that, by its very nature, cannot exist in the way we imagine. Like attempting to describe the color of diligence, we&amp;rsquo;re trying to assign concrete properties to an abstract concept that exists only in our minds. The universe, in its fundamental state, operates on physical laws and chemical reactions, with no inherent purpose woven into its fabric.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/exploit/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/exploit/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="control-the-masses-by-controlling-their-minds"&gt;Control the Masses by Controlling Their Minds&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout history, powerful individuals and groups have exerted influence over the masses through the manipulation of thoughts, beliefs, and perceptions. The ability to control the minds of large populations has proven to be a cornerstone of maintaining authority, implementing agendas, and shaping societies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Role of Communication and Media&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most potent tools for influencing the minds of the masses is control over communication channels. Historically, monarchs, dictators, and religious leaders controlled the flow of information through proclamations, sermons, and censorship. In modern times, this power has shifted to mass media, including newspapers, radio, television, and social media platforms.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/fep/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/fep/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="自由能原则"&gt;自由能原则&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reward / Utility / Score / Value&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Surprise / Prediction Error / Chunkify&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id="two-kinds-of-predictin-errors"&gt;Two Kinds of Predictin Errors&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pragmatic or Reward Prediction Error&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Epistemic or Lexeme Prediction Error&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But they are the same:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In reinforcement learning or decision theory, the complement of surprise is often called value (or utility).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Low surprise = high expected value (your predictions about the world are confirmed).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;High surprise = low value (your model didn’t anticipate what happened).&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/follow/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/follow/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="social-conformity"&gt;Social Conformity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social conformity is the tendency for individuals to align their behaviors, beliefs, and attitudes with those of their social group or broader society. This fundamental aspect of human behavior shapes everything from our daily choices in fashion and language to our deeper beliefs and moral values. It represents our innate drive to fit in, belong, and maintain social harmony within our communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Psychology Behind Conformity
Humans conform for several compelling psychological reasons. First, there&amp;rsquo;s informational influence – we often look to others for cues about appropriate behavior, especially in ambiguous situations. When unsure about how to act, we observe those around us and mirror their behavior, assuming they possess knowledge we lack. Second, normative influence drives conformity through our desire to be accepted and avoid rejection. The fear of standing out or facing social disapproval can be a powerful motivator for conforming to group norms.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/foundation/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/foundation/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="少点主义多点经济"&gt;少点主义，多点经济&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;痴迷于问题，而不是方案，或者是自我形象&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-foundation-metric-discussing-money-first-until-its-not-needed"&gt;The Foundation Metric: Discussing Money First, Until It&amp;rsquo;s Not Needed&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The previous critiques of monetary worship often overlook a fundamental truth: before money can be a distraction, it must first be a foundation. The principle encapsulated by &amp;ldquo;Discussing Money First, Until It&amp;rsquo;s Not Needed&amp;rdquo; posits that financial security is not the goal of human flourishing, but the precondition for it. Money operates as the indispensable base layer—the foundation metric—that stabilizes life and liberates attention, allowing the individual to finally engage with the difficult, unquantifiable metrics of meaning, virtue, and character. We must prioritize the discussion of finance until the need for that discussion effectively disappears.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/fraud/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/fraud/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="都是为了你好"&gt;都是为了你好&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id="永远战时状态"&gt;永远战时状态&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id="割喉降血压"&gt;割喉降血压&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id="都是一家人"&gt;都是一家人&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id="身上满是标签"&gt;身上满是标签&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id="黑社会手段"&gt;黑社会手段&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id="通过洗脑注入新词"&gt;通过洗脑，注入新词&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id="scam-of-the-authoritarian-regime-common-tactics-of-manipulation"&gt;Scam of the Authoritarian Regime: Common Tactics of Manipulation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scams and authoritarian regimes may seem worlds apart, but they share remarkable similarities in their manipulation techniques. Both exploit fundamental human psychological vulnerabilities to control, influence, and ultimately extract value from their targets. Understanding these parallels can help us recognize and resist these tactics in various contexts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Creating an Aura of Authority
Both scammers and authoritarian regimes invest heavily in creating and maintaining an image of authority and infallibility. Scammers might pose as government officials, technical experts, or successful business figures. They display fake credentials, testimonials, and social proof to establish trust. Similarly, authoritarian regimes build personality cults around leaders, control media narratives to portray themselves as all-knowing, and create elaborate displays of power through military parades or grandiose infrastructure projects.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/free-energy/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/free-energy/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="free-energy"&gt;Free Energy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the pandemic in 2021, I bought a second-hand Wii U online. It was cheap but came with one drawback: the entire interface was in Japanese. That frustration turned into motivation. Over the next five years, I studied Japanese on Duolingo. As a native Chinese speaker fluent in English, learning Japanese opened doors to ways of thinking and living that physics and computer science could never teach me.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/game/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/game/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="游戏"&gt;游戏&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;FEP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;求知，求胜，都是为了降低 prediction error&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/halo/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/halo/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="光环效应"&gt;光环效应&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;特征显著不代表是主要原因&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id="什么是光环效应"&gt;什么是光环效应&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;光环效应是指人们在认知和评价他人或事物时，往往会因为某一个突出的特征（优点或缺点）而对整体产生偏颇的印象。如果一个人有显著的优点，人们容易高估他在其他方面的表现。如果一个人有明显的缺点，人们也容易低估他在其他方面的能力。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;例如：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;长得好看的人常常被认为更聪明、更善良。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;知名公司出身的人，在新工作中更容易被认为能力强。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;广告代言：明星的光环会让人以为产品本身也优秀。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id="为什么会有光环效应"&gt;为什么会有光环效应&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;认知经济性（Cognitive Economy），人类大脑在面对复杂信息时，倾向于寻找捷径。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;大脑里的知识网络是联想式的：“漂亮”常与“聪明”“善良”“受欢迎”一起被激活。“地位高”常与“能力强”“值得信赖”联系在一起。这种自动的语义联结让某一个特质的光环影响了整体判断。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;快速归纳提高了生存效率。缺点是，现代社会复杂化后，这种机制容易导致偏差。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;光环效应产生，是因为大脑为了节省能量，会用局部特征推断整体；情绪、联想、进化需要和社会文化又共同放大了这种倾向。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;光环效应是大脑在自由能原理下的一种“认知压缩”：通过一个显著特征覆盖其他特征，降低了信息处理的复杂度，却牺牲了准确性。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="光环效应的害处"&gt;光环效应的害处&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在感情中，人们容易被对方某个优点吸引，而忽视潜在风险。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;一个领导人因为在某一方面有突出成就（如战争胜利、经济建设、个人魅力），大众就倾向于认为他在其他方面同样正确、无懈可击。这种“光环”逐渐被放大成全能化、神化，导致社会缺乏理性批判，最终形成个人崇拜。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;希特勒因演讲能力和民族主义口号获得光环，被认定为“民族拯救者”。结果导致德国社会整体陷入非理性，最终引发二战和大规模屠杀。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;邪教领袖往往利用光环效应，把自己塑造成“神圣化身”，追随者完全丧失独立思考，最终甚至付出生命代价（如琼斯镇惨案）。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;消灭异议：光环效应让人们对批评充耳不闻，甚至敌视反对意见。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;失去纠错机制：任何政策或决策都被当成“正确”，错误会被无限放大。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;集体非理性：大众不再根据事实判断，而是盲从“光环”。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="如何避免"&gt;如何避免&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;不要用单一特质（外貌、学历、职位）来推断整体，而是把评价分解为多个独立维度（能力、责任心、沟通力、成果）&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;不要凭第一印象做决定，给自己更多观察和收集证据的机会。复盘思考：在做决定后问自己：“我是不是被某个突出的点吸引，从而忽视了其他证据？”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="贝叶斯解释"&gt;贝叶斯解释&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;代价敏感的最优性：在有限时间与评估成本下，使用强线索进行快速决策能提高期望效用（少采样也能足够好）。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;光环效应之所以“看似合理”，是因为在真实相关存在、成本受限时，用强线索做贝叶斯更新能快速降低不确定性。它的局限在于人们常把先验与似然比高估，忽略基率与情境依赖，并在代价敏感的任务中过早停止采样，最终从“合理的启发式”滑向“系统性偏差”。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在分层贝叶斯或卡尔曼更新里，把先验或单一线索的精度设得太高，会让后续证据进不来，形成自我强化的“光环”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;多维证据，分条件更新：把“显著特征”与独立证据分开更新，避免单一线索吞没一切。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;代价敏感采样：在高代价决策里，提高证据阈值，延迟决策。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;抑制过度精度：在模型里限制先验或单一线索的精度权重，保证后续证据能改写判断。&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/handcuffs/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/handcuffs/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="golden-handcuffs-the-panic-and-constraints-of-wealth"&gt;Golden Handcuffs: The Panic and Constraints of Wealth&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Introduction: Wealth as a Double-Edged Sword&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The phrase “golden handcuffs” evokes an image of luxury and captivity at once. On one hand, financial security is prized; on the other, it binds people to jobs, lifestyles, or decisions that restrict freedom. Understanding why people fear financial insecurity, and how that fear itself can impose limitations, is crucial to navigating a healthy relationship with money.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/incentive/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/incentive/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="the-importance-of-counterbalance"&gt;The Importance of Counterbalance&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without checks and balances, slavery will breed; cooperation based on restraint is merely a temporary gift.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;没有制衡，就会滋生奴役；基于道德的合理，只是一时的恩赐&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In every system—be it business, politics, the workplace, or law—cooperation and fairness are contingent on the presence of counterbalances. Without counterbalance, the natural tendencies of individuals or organizations to exploit their power and engage in wrongful behaviors become unchecked, leading to negative consequences for society as a whole. When wrongdoings go unpunished, and those in power are not held accountable, a lack of cooperation and trust begins to erode the integrity of the system. This essay explores how the absence of counterbalance leads to exploitation and suffering, using examples from business, politics, work environments, and law to highlight the importance of balance in fostering a fair and just society.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/intangible/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/intangible/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Courtesy and Kindness Is Money as Well&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In everyday life we are accustomed to thinking of “money” only as coins, notes, or digital balances. Yet there is another form of capital—less visible but no less powerful—that is earned and spent constantly: courtesy and kindness. Just as financial currency circulates to sustain an economy, small acts of respect and generosity circulate to sustain the social networks and reputations on which all economic and personal success depends.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/intercept/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/intercept/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="immediate-gratification"&gt;Immediate Gratification&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Immediate gratification is a concept deeply embedded in human behavior and psychology. It refers to the desire to experience pleasure or fulfillment without delay. While the lure of immediate rewards can sometimes be beneficial, it often stands in stark contrast to the virtues of patience and long-term planning, leading to various consequences in personal, social, and economic contexts. Through examples from daily life, history, and modern technology, the significance and impact of immediate gratification become clearer.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/invest/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/invest/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="wealth-by-investing"&gt;Wealth by Investing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In today’s world, building wealth is a goal that many people share. While some choose to earn money by providing services directly, such as working a job or running a business, others opt for a different path: investing. Investing involves using the money and resources you already have to make more money over time. This essay will explore how investing works, how it can lead to financial freedom, and the risks involved in this approach to building wealth.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/jump/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/jump/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="jumping-to-conclusions"&gt;Jumping To Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jumping to conclusions is a common cognitive bias where individuals make quick judgments or decisions without sufficient evidence or analysis. This behavior is often impulsive and rooted in cognitive shortcuts our brains use to process information efficiently. While this tendency can sometimes lead to accurate conclusions, more often it results in misunderstandings, miscommunication, or poor decision-making. The causes of jumping to conclusions are varied, but they generally stem from emotional responses, social influences, and inherent cognitive biases. To understand the nature of this phenomenon, it is helpful to examine its psychological underpinnings and real-life implications.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/language/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/language/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="model-training-and-predition"&gt;Model Training and Predition&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id="the-continuous-process-of-model-training"&gt;The Continuous Process of Model Training&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the analogy of life as a language model (LLM), the foundational process is Model Training and Predition:&lt;/p&gt;
$$
p(\text{new model} \mid \text{old model}, \text{feedback})
$$&lt;p&gt;The &amp;ldquo;old model&amp;rdquo; represents our initial state: genetics, temperament, and early childhood conditioning. &amp;ldquo;Feedback&amp;rdquo; encompasses every sensory input, consequence of action, moment of learning, and cultural encounter. The &amp;ldquo;new model&amp;rdquo; is the updated self—the person we become an instant later. This formula describes personal growth as continuous Bayesian updating. We do not learn through massive, singular changes, but through micro-adjustments in the weighted probability of our internal parameters, driven by experience. Evolution is the ultimate training run, and personal development is fine-tuning.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/learn/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/learn/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="熟练lexeme的价值"&gt;熟练lexeme的价值&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;大多数学习领域都遵循帕累托分布：大约 20% 的核心概念能带来 80% 的成果。如果能专注于那关键的 20%，也就是核心 lexeme，你就掌握了这门学科的“脊梁”。其余的一切都是这些核心的变体和扩展。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;当核心 lexeme 被牢固内化后，大脑会自动把新信息“打包”进这些已有的模式里。你不必从零开始处理每个细节，而是把新数据归入熟悉的“类目”。这极大减轻了认知负荷，让学习新材料变得直观。就像搭建大楼：只要地基和支柱稳固，后续的楼层和房间就能顺理成章地加上去。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;这意味着高阶主题能更快被掌握，因为它们依托在你已经拥有的基础上。核心 lexeme 的收益是指数级的：它们像杠杆一样，能让练习的每一分钟产出更大效果。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;学习效率的提升&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;移除瓶颈：通过优先掌握少数关键概念，你能绕开学习中最重的阻碍。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;释放工作记忆：你不用记忆和拼凑大量分散的事实，而是直接把新知识与核心锚点挂钩。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;快速正反馈：高价值 lexeme 训练带来的早期成果，能增强信心与动力。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;自动化技能：一旦内化，它们会从费力的步骤变为直觉反应。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;自动化与模式识别&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;核心 lexeme 的练习最终会发展成 信号—反应反射：看到信号，大脑几乎自动给出反应。这就像认字或识别棋局形态一样，不再消耗太多注意力。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;这种 自动提取 能释放工作记忆，把注意力转向更复杂的问题层面，加速技能掌握。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;限定假设空间与降低歧义&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;每次学会一个 lexeme，相当于在缩小解释新信息的可能性空间。你不再需要在几十种可能性中做选择，而只需在已有 lexeme 对应的有限几种里判断。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;标签化作用：lexeme 像给信息流打上“标签”，帮助大脑聚焦关键信息，忽略无关细节。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;跨领域桥梁：核心 lexeme 往往具备迁移性，能在不同情境下发挥作用，提升类比与创造力。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;抗遗忘性与错误修正&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;高效 lexeme 在频繁曝光与反馈中不断被强化，逐渐成为 抗衰减节点。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;这种节点更难被遗忘。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;当出错时，只需调整该 lexeme，本体模型不会被大面积破坏，保证整体连贯性。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;传统学习方式的问题&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;传统教材往往：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;把每个定理、推论、特例一股脑呈现。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;让学生淹没在符号和边角知识中，难以辨别重点。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;导致工作记忆过载，只能记住零散事实，却难以流畅调用关键概念。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;这种方式平等对待每个细节，结果是把大量时间浪费在低价值内容上，反而忽视了能打开 80% 大门的 20% 核心。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;课堂学习里，师生常陷入“欲速则不达”的陷阱：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;错觉的简单：专家眼里的直观概念，对初学者可能暗藏陷阱。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;话题推进过快：学生没能整合核心，就被迫切换话题，导致碎片化学习。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;频繁失败：基础不牢固，面对进阶内容时屡屡受挫，信心下降。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;高效练习的意义&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;与其被动跟随教材的海量练习，不如专注于少量 信号—反应训练。它们能产生最大化的回报。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;噪音剔除：非核心细节统统当作噪音忽略。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;积极反馈：每次练习都带来可见进步，增强成就感。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;神经机制视角&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;学习中的每个特征都有变异和噪音。要想真正编码为 lexeme，需要足够多的样本来使模式信号高于噪音。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;稳定阈值：只有当大脑对某模式的置信度超过某一阈值，才会分配资源把它固化为持久记忆。&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/levels/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/levels/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="分级"&gt;分级&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h3 id="the-high-cost-of-low-utility-why-we-learn-the-wrong-things"&gt;The High Cost of Low Utility: Why We Learn the Wrong Things&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We operate in a world defined by the accumulation of information, yet true wisdom—the knowledge essential for living a fulfilling life—often remains elusive. The paradox lies in the structure of knowledge itself: a vast landscape where we are consistently compelled to master low-utility information at the expense of high-reward understanding. This inefficiency in learning can be analyzed by grading knowledge units, or lexemes, based on three critical attributes: Utility (Reward Power), Frequency (Applicability), and Difficulty (Mastery Cost). By applying this framework, it becomes clear why modern systems, from education to digital culture, often trick us into acquiring skills and facts that offer minimal payoff for a better life.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/lexemes-list/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/lexemes-list/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="list"&gt;List&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id="web"&gt;Web&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flex and Grid&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id="design"&gt;Design&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kerning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/lexemes/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/lexemes/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="lexemes"&gt;Lexemes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id="人脑的工作原理"&gt;人脑的工作原理&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3 id="markov-blanket"&gt;Markov Blanket&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;如果变化环境，这个词汇还是能够独立出现并稳定存在。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在一个系统里，马尔可夫毯定义了一个节点（变量）与外部世界之间的边界。
给定马尔可夫毯，节点与其他所有节点条件独立。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;也就是说，知道了马尔可夫毯，就不需要知道更远的节点信息，因为它们对其不再有额外的影响。这就像是一个“信息屏障”。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;感官输入（视觉）进入马尔可夫毯&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;内部状态推断 latent variable：“这是猫”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;大脑用 lexeme “猫” 来编码它（压缩 + 可交流）&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;行动输出（比如抚摸或喂食）再通过毯子反馈到外部&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;只要知道了 X 的马尔可夫毯，世界上其他变量对 X 的因果影响都被“屏蔽”了。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;所以马尔可夫毯可以看成是 因果作用的边界。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在因果推理里（Pearl 的 do-calculus），当你对某个节点施加干预 其因果效应只会通过 马尔可夫毯定义的通路 往外扩散。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;毯子之外的因果路径要么被阻断，要么只能间接体现。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;所以你可以把 因果效应的传播半径 看作是 Markov Blanket 的边界。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;烧开的水壶 → 水与空气的接触面就是一个边界，热量可以通过蒸汽扩散出去，但分子不会穿透金属壁。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;半导体芯片 → 边界条件定义了电流如何输入输出，内部电荷的动力学必须遵守边界约束。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;总结：边界条件决定了 能量、物质和信息 的流入流出。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Karl Friston 的自由能原理其实就是把“热力学边界”套用到认知系统：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;生物体（系统）必须与外界交换能量和信息才能维持稳定（homeostasis）。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;这种交换不是无限的，而是被马尔可夫毯限定。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;自由能最小化就像物理里的熵增约束：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;系统要保持结构不崩溃，就必须通过边界调节输入输出，把不确定性压缩。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在物理里，你不会追踪每个分子的状态，只看边界上的平均量（温度、压力）。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在认知里，你不会追踪世界所有变量，只压缩成 lexeme（“猫”“桌子”“敌意”）。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lexeme 就是大脑给马尔可夫毯的“边界条件”做的符号化压缩：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;内部潜变量太复杂&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;外部输入太庞杂&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;必须压缩成可操作的 lexeme，才能降低 surprise 并进行因果推理。&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/limit/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/limit/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="the-gilded-cage-and-the-ballot-box-examining-extreme-wealth-and-democratic-competence"&gt;The Gilded Cage and the Ballot Box: Examining Extreme Wealth and Democratic Competence&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pervasive tension between extreme wealth and popular sovereignty succinctly captures a core challenge in modern society: the relationship between massive private fortunes, citizens&amp;rsquo; access to information, and political power. This challenge forces us to confront two fundamental questions: Should a society permit the accumulation of massive, even colossal, fortunes? And should the perceived cognitive capacity or informational disadvantage of citizens disqualify them from fundamental decision-making rights? A balanced analysis suggests that while absolute prohibition of wealth is impractical and restricting democratic rights is dangerous, the current system requires radical institutional reforms focused on equitable education and wealth distribution to ensure a functioning, informed democracy.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/living/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/living/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="the-only-living-person-this-world-rises-for-you-and-it-will-collapse-entirely-because-of-you"&gt;The Only Living Person: This World Rises for You, and It Will Collapse Entirely Because of You&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The World Begins and Ends With the Self&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the moment you awaken to consciousness, reality appears. The light of the sun, the texture of the air, the colors of a friend’s smile—these are not separate from your experience but inseparable from it. In this view, your consciousness acts as the only true reference point; the world you know begins at your birth and will vanish at your death. In this sense, every individual is not merely “in” the world but also the central projector of their own universe.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/loss/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/loss/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="等效法"&gt;等效法&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a 9/11-scale tragedy (≈3,000 deaths) happened every single day starting on September 1, 1939 — the day World War II began — it would continue, day after day, all the way until September 11, 2001.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, the entire 62-year span between the start of WWII and the 9/11 attacks matches the scale of WWII’s estimated death toll of roughly 70 million people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;看过很多 911 的纪录片，事件发生时，我也有很深刻印象&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;知道死了很多人，造成了很深远的悲剧&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/luck/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/luck/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The Luck Factor — Why We Shouldn’t Deify Successful People&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Introduction: Success and Its Halo Effect
Modern culture tends to glorify those who achieve extraordinary success — founders of tech giants, athletes at the top of their sport, or celebrities whose careers skyrocket seemingly overnight. Books and articles dissect their routines, habits, and “mindsets,” treating them as living formulas for greatness. Yet this obsession with the so-called “secrets of success” often hides one of the most powerful forces at play: luck. When we deify successful people, we risk misunderstanding the role of randomness, timing, and social context in shaping outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/majority/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/majority/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="inclusion-and-welfare-most-people-should-see-themselves-as-part-of-the-majority"&gt;Inclusion and Welfare: Most People Should See Themselves as Part of the Majority&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Escaping the Elite Illusion
Many modern societies are built around the promise of upward mobility. Advertisements, social media, and corporate culture all suggest that with enough hard work and cleverness, anyone can become an elite—a CEO, a top performer, or a “little king” who controls resources. Yet mathematically, this cannot be true for everyone. By definition, elites are few. If most people orient their choices, politics, and social policies around the fantasy of becoming an elite, the resulting system will fail the majority. This is why embracing inclusion and welfare—seeing oneself as part of the majority—is essential for a healthy, stable society.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/merit/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/merit/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;《邪门的傲慢：是你能力不行还是环境太差？》&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="social-darwinism-the-inhumanity-of-meritocracy"&gt;Social Darwinism: The Inhumanity of Meritocracy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Introduction – From Survival of the Fittest to “Best Performer Wins”
Social Darwinism emerged in the late 19th century as a distortion of Charles Darwin’s theory of evolution. Instead of remaining a biological concept, “survival of the fittest” was extended to social and economic life, suggesting that the most successful individuals or groups were inherently superior. Modern meritocracy often inherits this same mindset. It appears humane—rewarding talent, effort, and achievement—but beneath its surface lies an impersonal system that can quietly strip away empathy, solidarity, and the social glue that binds communities together.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/metric/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/metric/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="the-limited-metric-why-not-everything-can-be-measured-by-money"&gt;The Limited Metric: Why Not Everything Can Be Measured by Money&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Money is, without question, the most powerful and widely accepted metric in the modern world. It is the language of commerce, a universal tool for allocating resources, measuring productivity, and facilitating exchange. However, the inclination to treat money as the only measure of value—a tendency increasingly pervasive in contemporary society—is a fundamental error. To quantify all of existence in monetary terms is to reduce complexity to a single, inadequate dimension, inevitably overlooking and devaluing the very elements that contribute most profoundly to human fulfillment, ethical governance, and societal well-being. Money is a powerful tool, but it is a disastrous master.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/model/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/model/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="all-models-are-wrong-some-are-useful"&gt;All Models Are Wrong. Some Are Useful&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The statistician George Box once noted that “all models are wrong, but some are useful,” a remark that highlights the complexity of how we understand the world through science. While this statement acknowledges the inherent imperfections in every scientific model, it by no means equates science with guesswork or superstition. On the contrary, science’s strength lies in its capacity to provide models that are profoundly reliable, massively supported by evidence, and demonstrably effective in real-world applications. Although we cannot logically exclude the faint philosophical possibility of even the best model failing in some unforeseen scenario, this is so exceedingly improbable that it remains, for all practical purposes, an empty concern. Our best models are not just convenient fictions; they are robust frameworks honed over generations of testing, refinement, and application, enabling us to navigate and control the world with extraordinary precision.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/passive/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/passive/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="passive-income-levels"&gt;Passive Income Levels&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1万每个月，需要本金250万&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2万每个月，需要本金500万，财富自由底线，“不怕失业”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5万每个月，需要本金1500万，高净值家庭（HNWI），百分之一（中国有2000万HNWI）&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10万每个月，需要本金2500万，高档次的财富自由&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;50万每个月，需要本金1.5亿，超高净值家庭（UHNW），两万分之一&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;中国有10万UHNW，美国有22万，全球有50万人。&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/primary/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/primary/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="restrained-perfection-the-ubiquity-of-the-8020-principle"&gt;Restrained Perfection: The Ubiquity of the 80/20 Principle”&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Introduction: The Power of Unequal Distribution&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 80/20 Principle—also called the Pareto Principle—describes how a small fraction of causes often produces a large share of effects. Originally observed in economics by Vilfredo Pareto, who noticed that 20% of people owned 80% of the land in Italy, the principle now appears everywhere: in business, learning, health, creativity, and personal life. Yet one key implication is often ignored: to live effectively, we must restrain our pursuit of perfection and embrace strategic imperfection.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/prior/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/prior/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="科学"&gt;科学&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id="没用的词汇"&gt;没用的词汇&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;我们把爱因斯坦放的很高的位置，但了解爱因斯坦，学会下面的方程&lt;/p&gt;
$$
R_{\mu \nu} - \frac{1}{2}g_{\mu \nu}R + \Lambda g_{\mu \nu} = \frac{8\pi G}{c^4}T_{\mu \nu}
$$&lt;p&gt;对你日常被没有什么用，也解释不了太多事情，也不会让你获得更快乐，理解这个方程的求知欲的满足是有的，但也不完全是有很高收益的行为。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;对于人类集体来说，这是一个很高的成就，爱因斯坦让这个物种对世界的理解更为深入了，但依旧，这是一个偏僻的词汇。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="最强的先验"&gt;最强的先验&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在贝叶斯大脑假说中，大脑被建模为一个推理机器。它不断接收感官输入（evidence），并用内部生成模型（generative model）来预测和解释外界。更新规则是典型的贝叶斯推断：&lt;/p&gt;
$$
Posterior \propto Likelihood \times Prior
$$&lt;p&gt;其中 &lt;strong&gt;prior&lt;/strong&gt; 决定了大脑在解释数据时的起点。如果某个先验过于强大，那么无论新的数据如何，它都很难被修正。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;物理学&lt;/strong&gt;恰恰就是这种最强的先验之一。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在 &lt;strong&gt;自由能原理 (FEP)&lt;/strong&gt; 的框架下，生物系统的目标是最小化 &lt;strong&gt;预测误差（prediction error）&lt;/strong&gt; 或其上界 &lt;strong&gt;自由能（free energy）&lt;/strong&gt;。也就是说，代理体必须构建一个生成模型，能够让外部输入尽量符合它的预测。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在这个过程中，有些预测误差是可以容忍并更新的（比如文化差异、社会习俗），但有些误差是几乎无法更新的，因为它们对应着 &lt;strong&gt;生存所必需的感官—运动约束&lt;/strong&gt;。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;物理学规律正是这种约束的抽象化：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;重力&lt;/strong&gt;：如果代理不先验地相信“物体会落下”，它无法安全行动。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;能量守恒&lt;/strong&gt;：如果不内置能量约束，它会不断生成不可实现的行动计划。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;时空连续性&lt;/strong&gt;：如果不假设事件有稳定的时空关系，它无法形成持久的因果模型。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;这些规律形成了“饥渴级”的强先验，因为一旦不遵守，它立刻会导致代理体失去生存的可能。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在贝叶斯意义上，饥饿和口渴是极难被更新的先验，因为它们与代理体的 &lt;strong&gt;生存边界条件（Markov blanket）&lt;/strong&gt; 强耦合。没有水，系统会解体；没有能量，系统无法维持远离熵增的状态。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;物理学的规律处于同一层次：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;它们并非仅仅是经验积累的结果，而是直接嵌入 &lt;strong&gt;生存必须满足的生成模型&lt;/strong&gt; 中。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;它们决定了代理体如何在世界中保持自身边界，如何行动，如何预测未来。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;就像口渴无法被“观念”更新掉一样，物理学规律也无法被简单的证据推翻。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;因此，在所有可能的先验里，物理学规律拥有最大的信息增益比率：它们带来的 prediction error reduction 是不可替代的。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;与物理学相比，其他知识领域（社会学、心理学、经济学）则属于更高层次的生成模型。它们虽然能被修正，但底层仍然依赖物理的硬约束：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;经济模型必须符合能量和物质的守恒。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;心理学理论最终要符合神经元放电与代谢的物理过程。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;社会传播模型要受限于光速与信道容量的物理极限。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;这些上层模型可以灵活更新，而物理规律作为深层先验几乎不可更新。这就是为什么物理学是“所有解释的先验”，是其他模型的边界条件。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;从 &lt;strong&gt;自由能原理&lt;/strong&gt; 和 &lt;strong&gt;贝叶斯大脑&lt;/strong&gt; 的角度看，物理学不是我们选择相信的东西，而是我们在建模世界时不可避免的结构。它像饥饿与口渴一样，构成了我们最强的先验偏好。&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/product/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/product/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="all-products-are-dictionaries"&gt;All products are dictionaries&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Product as Dictionary: Turning Learned Vocabulary into Executable Tools&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Products as Faster Paths to Solutions&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At their core, products exist to shrink the time and effort between a problem and its solution. Just as learning a new word speeds up your “next word prediction” in conversation or writing, using a well-designed product accelerates your ability to act in the world. A camera, for example, lets memory leap from the fragile and fleeting biological substrate of the brain to a durable and easily retrievable format. A search engine transforms hours of library work into seconds of query time. Both vocabulary and products serve the same function: they encode complexity into accessible, reusable units.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/proxy2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/proxy2/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="专注解决问题而不是解决方案"&gt;专注解决问题，而不是解决方案&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fall in Love with the Problem, Not the Solution&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This principle urges us to stay devoted to understanding and alleviating the real issues at hand rather than clinging to the first method we believe will fix them. History shows that when individuals, movements, or governments confuse the two—when they treat their preferred solutions as sacred—disaster can follow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A problem is an underlying condition or need in reality; a solution is merely a hypothesis about how to address it. Problems endure regardless of our theories. If we equate our favored solution with the problem itself, we risk losing touch with what we’re actually trying to improve. This cognitive trap happens because humans crave certainty and dislike the discomfort of ambiguity. Once we identify with a solution, changing our minds feels like losing part of our identity.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/rarity/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/rarity/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="rarity"&gt;Rarity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rarity is a fundamental concept that permeates various aspects of our understanding of the world. Whether applied to intellectual abilities, wealth, or natural phenomena, rarity denotes something that is uncommon or infrequent within a given context. While recognizing rarity can provide valuable insights into the diversity and distribution of traits and resources, it also carries potential pitfalls, particularly when rarity is misconstrued as a measure of worth or goodness. This essay explores the significance of rarity in comprehending the world, highlighting both its utility and the misconceptions that can arise from its misinterpretation.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/ref/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/ref/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="references"&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id="free-energe-principle"&gt;Free-Energe Principle&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Friston, K. The free-energy principle: a unified brain theory?. Nat Rev Neurosci 11, 127–138 (2010). &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nrn2787"&gt;https://doi.org/10.1038/nrn2787&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cutts, E. The free‑energy principle: Can one idea explain why everything exists? New Scientist, (3513), pp.32-36.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id="aritificial-intelligence"&gt;Aritificial intelligence&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Russell, S. J., &amp;amp; Norvig, P. (2020). Artificial intelligence: A modern approach (4th ed.). Pearson.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id="indivisual-behavior"&gt;Indivisual Behavior&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kahneman, D. (2011). Thinking, fast and slow. Farrar, Straus and Giroux.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id="group-behaviour"&gt;Group Behaviour&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Smith, H. (1976). The Russians. New York, NY: Ballantine Books.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/refute/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/refute/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="refute-as-if-a-duel"&gt;Refute as if a duel.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve all felt it: someone says something we disagree with, and before they even finish their sentence, a counterargument forms in our mind. Our heart rate picks up, our inner lawyer stands up, and we’re ready to strike back. This urge to quickly refute feels like defending truth — but more often it’s defending our ego. And while it offers short-term relief, it quietly steals our best chances to grow.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/rich/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/rich/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="winning-over-learning-why-having-money-does-not-mean-having-wisdom"&gt;Winning Over Learning: Why Having Money Does Not Mean Having Wisdom&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why Devotion to Money Can Undermine True Wisdom&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Introduction: The Split Between Wealth and Wisdom
Modern culture often equates financial success with intelligence. High net worth individuals are celebrated as geniuses, their opinions on unrelated topics treated as inherently credible. Yet the reality is that wealth and wisdom are not synonymous. In fact, dedicating one’s life to accumulating money can actively erode the conditions needed to develop deep insight and true intellectual skill.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/save/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/save/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="money-making-chase"&gt;Money Making Chase&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our modern society&amp;rsquo;s relentless pursuit of financial success, we often lose sight of the profound truth that life encompasses far more than the accumulation of wealth. The fixation on money as the ultimate measure of success has become deeply entrenched in our collective psyche, shaped by various historical and social forces, and reveals a troubling pattern of fixed mindset thinking and cognitive limitation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This obsession with monetary gain can be traced to several root causes. The rise of consumer capitalism has created a system where success is predominantly measured in financial terms. Media and advertising constantly bombard us with messages linking happiness to purchasing power, creating artificial needs and desires. Social media amplifies this further, with displays of luxury lifestyles and material achievements becoming the default markers of success.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/science/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/science/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="consensus-of-knowledge-what-kind-of-vocabulary-deserves-to-spread-what-is-the-nature-of-science"&gt;Consensus of Knowledge: What Kind of Vocabulary Deserves to Spread? What Is the Nature of Science?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Introduction – Knowledge as a Collective Lexicon
Human progress depends on an ever-expanding lexicon of concepts, terms, and metaphors. Every society builds and refines its vocabulary to describe reality, from the simplest folk wisdom to the most advanced scientific theories. The question “What kind of vocabulary deserves to spread?” is essentially about the quality and purpose of our shared language. Scientific terms, technical concepts, and new metaphors are not just labels; they are compressed packets of collective experience, waiting to be mined, tested, and transmitted.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/services/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/services/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="from-scholar-to-exploiter"&gt;From Scholar to Exploiter&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In traditional Chinese society, the role of the scholar held immense prestige and significance. Rooted in Confucian values, scholars were expected to dedicate their lives to learning, moral development, and ultimately serving as government officials. This esteemed path was seen as a way to contribute to the welfare of the state and society. However, when examined through the lenses of value creation and economic justice, this cultural cornerstone reveals a more complex and often problematic reality: the transformation of scholarly excellence into a pathway for systematic exploitation. This essay explores how the revered journey from scholar to government official can sometimes lead to the misuse of power and the exploitation of others, highlighting the importance of ethical governance and the balance between authority and accountability.
The Scholar-Official Tradition in Chinese History
The tradition of scholars becoming government officials in China dates back to the imperial examination system established during the Sui Dynasty (581–618 AD) and refined over centuries. This system was designed to select the most capable and morally upright individuals to govern the vast empire. Scholars devoted themselves to rigorous study of Confucian texts, philosophy, and administrative skills, aspiring to serve the state with integrity and wisdom.
Historically, this system aimed to create a meritocratic bureaucracy where officials were chosen based on their knowledge and ethical standards rather than their family connections or wealth. The ideal was that these scholar-officials would implement just policies, promote social harmony, and ensure the well-being of the populace.
Value Creation and Ethical Governance
At its core, the scholar-official system was intended to foster value creation through enlightened governance. Scholar-officials were expected to apply their education and moral training to create policies that benefited society, promoted education, maintained social order, and encouraged economic development. Their deep understanding of philosophy and ethics was supposed to guide their decision-making, ensuring that their governance was fair and just.
In this ideal scenario, the pathway from scholar to official was a means of uplifting society, creating value by addressing the needs of the people, and fostering economic justice. Scholar-officials were seen as stewards of the public good, using their knowledge to create a prosperous and harmonious state.
The Shift Towards Exploitation
However, the reality of the scholar-official system often deviated from its noble intentions. Several factors contributed to this shift from value creation to exploitation:
a. Concentration of Power
As scholars ascended to high-ranking government positions, they accumulated significant power and influence. Without adequate checks and balances, this concentration of power could lead to abuses. Scholar-officials might prioritize their interests or those of their peers over the needs of the general populace, leading to corruption and exploitation.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/slope/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/slope/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="metric"&gt;Metric&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evolutionary and Social Roots
Humans evolved in small groups where status and belonging meant survival. Comparing ourselves to others helped us gauge our position in the group and adjust our behavior accordingly. Even today, seeing where we “stand” relative to others feels like an instinct.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shortcut for Evaluating Success
Metrics and rankings are simple heuristics. Instead of deeply evaluating each person or opportunity, we use numbers, likes, and titles to instantly estimate who is “doing well.” It’s efficient, even if crude.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/smart/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/smart/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="there-is-no-golden-house-in-books-why-having-wisdom-does-not-guarantee-wealth"&gt;There Is No Golden House in Books: Why Having Wisdom Does Not Guarantee Wealth&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why a Knowledgeable or Smart Person Might Not Be Rich&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Introduction: The Myth of the Golden House
For centuries, many cultures have celebrated the idea that studying hard will naturally lead to wealth and social elevation. In Chinese, the saying “书中自有黄金屋” (“in books there is a golden house”) captures this belief. Yet reality often disappoints. A person may be brilliant, deeply educated, and widely knowledgeable but still struggle financially. This contradiction is not an accident — it arises from how knowledge, labor, markets, and social systems interact.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/solve/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/solve/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="creating-wealth-is-solving-problems"&gt;Creating Wealth is Solving Problems&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In today&amp;rsquo;s world, people hold various common beliefs about money and wealth creation. Many see money as something to be earned through hard work, inherited, or accumulated through investments. Some believe wealth comes primarily from owning assets, playing the stock market, or climbing the corporate ladder. Others view it as a finite resource to be competed for, where one person&amp;rsquo;s gain must be another&amp;rsquo;s loss. These perspectives, while containing elements of truth, miss a deeper fundamental principle about how new wealth is actually created in society. When we look beyond money as just currency or numbers in accounts, we can see that real wealth creation follows a remarkably simple principle: it comes from solving problems for others.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/standard/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/standard/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="the-bourgeois-lifestyle"&gt;The Bourgeois Lifestyle&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The term &amp;ldquo;bourgeoisie&amp;rdquo; originated in medieval France, referring to the middle class of urban dwellers who existed between the peasantry and nobility. Today, it describes a lifestyle characterized by upper-middle-class values, material comfort, and cultural sophistication. This lifestyle has evolved significantly from its historical roots but maintains distinct characteristics that set it apart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Core Characteristics
The bourgeois lifestyle is typically characterized by financial stability, emphasis on education, cultural refinement, and material comfort. Those living this lifestyle often prioritize career advancement, maintain professional occupations, and place high value on formal education and intellectual pursuits. Their homes are usually well-appointed, located in desirable neighborhoods, and furnished with quality items that reflect both comfort and status.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/startup/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/startup/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="finding-the-lands-a-journey-from-soil-to-silicon"&gt;Finding the Lands: A Journey from Soil to Silicon&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout history, the concept of &amp;ldquo;land&amp;rdquo; has evolved, yet it remains a symbol of power, wealth, and privilege. From the ancient battles for fertile soil to the modern struggles for financial dominance and technological monopoly, the quest for land has been a metaphorical and literal journey that defines class divisions and the human condition. In this essay, we will explore how land has served as the key to societal hierarchies, from ancient agricultural societies to the tech-driven economies of today. As we will see, the search for land—whether in the form of territory, capital, or innovation—has been a constant in the pursuit of a privileged life, one marked by comfort, security, and influence.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/surprise/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/surprise/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="新词"&gt;新词&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FEP says: any system (like a brain) must minimize surprise (prediction error) by updating its internal model of the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To do that, it builds latent representations (hidden states) that explain incoming sensations and signals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In humans, these latent states are often expressed through concepts and words&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A new lexeme in science/economics (say “inflation”) is not just a word, but a chunked model of patterns in the world:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before: the student sees prices rising, wages shifting, government printing money, but all feels disconnected → high surprise, fragmented predictions.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/surprize/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/surprize/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="surprize"&gt;Surprize&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Skinner’s Box Setup&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A rat presses a lever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes it gets food (reward).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the rat gets food when it did not expect it, that’s reward exceeds expectation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In reinforcement learning, this is the positive reward prediction error (RPE).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why It Feels Good (Reward Signal)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The unexpected food provides new evidence that the world is better (more rewarding) than predicted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dopamine neurons fire to signal this positive surprise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In FEP terms, this means the brain updates its model to reduce free energy:&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/tradeoff/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/tradeoff/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="tradeoff"&gt;Tradeoff&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;High Quality and Cheap&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Accuracy and High Speed&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/tribalism/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/tribalism/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="nationalism-as-an-extension-of-personal-narcissism"&gt;Nationalism as an Extension of Personal Narcissism&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nationalism, when examined through the lens of psychology and cognitive science, reveals itself as a manifestation of both personal narcissism and cognitive limitations. This dual framework helps explain why nationalist ideologies often resist rational argument and persist despite contrary evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At its core, narcissism is characterized by an inflated sense of self-importance, a need for admiration, and a lack of empathy for others. Similarly, nationalism often exhibits these same traits on a collective scale. The cognitive limitations that frequently accompany nationalist thinking amplify these narcissistic tendencies, creating a self-reinforcing cycle of simplified thinking and grandiose self-perception.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/turing/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/turing/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Turing and P/NP: The Limits of Determinism and Irreducible Complexity
Introduction&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alan Turing’s foundational work in the 1930s gave us the theoretical framework for computation. By introducing the Turing machine and the concept of decidability, he effectively defined the limits of what can be computed by any deterministic procedure. Decades later, the P versus NP problem emerged as one of the central open questions in computer science. It asks whether every problem whose solution can be verified quickly (NP) can also be solved quickly (P). Together, Turing’s ideas and the P/NP dilemma illuminate two fundamental boundaries: the theoretical limit of deterministic computation, and the possible irreducibility of certain forms of complexity.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/worship/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/worship/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="the-deification-of-the-dollar-simplicity-scarcity-and-the-human-urge"&gt;The Deification of the Dollar: Simplicity, Scarcity, and the Human Urge&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Money, when transformed from a tool of exchange into the ultimate standard of existence, becomes an object of worship. This phenomenon, this Deification of the Dollar, is not an accident of history but a consequence of three intersecting forces: the irresistible simplicity of the monetary metric, the inherent difficulty of articulating non-monetary value, and the deep-seated psychological vulnerabilities of human nature. We turn to money not because it perfectly measures worth, but because it offers the easiest and most universally accepted answer to the difficult question of &amp;ldquo;How well am I doing?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title/><link>https://yingkui.com/mv/wrong/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://yingkui.com/mv/wrong/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;迷信作为 lexeme 股票&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;迷信&lt;/strong&gt;（fortune, fate, 风水, 占卜…）其实就是一个“解释世界的词位”。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;它表面上给人一种 &lt;strong&gt;确定感&lt;/strong&gt;：“事情这样发生，是因为天意/命运/神灵”。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;所以短期看起来很诱人：不需要推理、不需要学习，立刻获得一个解释。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;从投资角度看，这就像一只 &lt;strong&gt;骗子股&lt;/strong&gt;：包装很华丽，承诺高回报，但没有真实价值支撑。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;为什么是“特别差”的股票&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;（1）高成本&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;你把注意力、金钱、时间投入进去（烧香、算命、买风水物件）。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;认知资源浪费掉，不再投入到科学、技能、长期成长里。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;就像持续往一个空壳公司砸钱。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;（2）虚假回报&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;给你一点 &lt;strong&gt;短期心理安慰&lt;/strong&gt;（焦虑暂时缓解）。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;但长期看，迷信不会真正降低不确定性，反而制造更多依赖。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;就像骗子公司发给你一张假的分红单。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;（3）长期负收益&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;你越依赖迷信，就越放弃现实中的因果学习（实验、验证、理性推理）。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;最终你的“认知投资组合”越来越贫瘠。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;就像重仓垃圾股，最后血本无归。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;为什么它比一般垃圾股还糟&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;普通垃圾 lexeme&lt;/strong&gt;（比如“面子”）至少还和社会互动有点关系。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;迷信 lexeme&lt;/strong&gt; 完全脱离因果机制，是“零价值 + 高依赖”的组合。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在投资学里，这不是垃圾股，而是 &lt;strong&gt;庞氏骗局 / 骗子产品&lt;/strong&gt;：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;靠不断骗取你新的注意力和投入维持。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;一旦拆穿，你发现多年投入毫无积累。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;自由能原则的解释&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;大脑用 lexeme 是为了降低自由能（解释世界）。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;迷信 lexeme 给你的是一种 &lt;strong&gt;虚假压缩&lt;/strong&gt;：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;它没有真的减少预测误差，只是把误差“打包藏起来”。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;结果是：每次遇到新事件，你又要额外解释为什么“天意这样安排”，自由能反而累积。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;就像财务报表造假，账面漂亮，实则亏空。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;迷信 = 骗子股票 / 庞氏骗局&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;成本极高&lt;/strong&gt;：投入注意力、金钱、时间。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;回报虚假&lt;/strong&gt;：只有短期心理安慰，没有长期因果解释力。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;长期崩盘&lt;/strong&gt;：让你丧失独立判断和学习能力，最后投资组合一文不值。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>